[
  {
    "question": "<b>The fourth king of this name claimed he had slept with over nine hundred women, and upon legitimizing his bastards, directly caused the Blackfyre rebellions. The second king of this name sparked the civil war known as the Dance of Dragons, and is remembered as one of the cruelest (*)</b> Targaryen rulers in history. An individual with this name was supposedly murdered during the Sack of King’s Landing, and epithets of other kings with this name include the Usurper, the Unlikely, and the Conqueror. For 10 points, what is this name also shared by Young Griff, Elia Martell’s son?",
    "answer": "<b><u>Aegon</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>The architect for this building envisioned it to be the grandest of all castles throughout Westeros, but failed to account for dragonfire. It was at this castle, many centuries later, that Jaime Lannister was named as a member of the Kingsguard. Soon after that, \"the moment all smiles died\" (*)</b> occurred here as well. No houses claim this castle to be their ancestral seat, and during the War of the Five Kings, the castle changed hands nearly a dozen times. This place is also the location of Jaime and Brienne’s famous bath scene. For 10 points, name the riverlands castle in which Arya Stark served as Roose Bolton’s cupbearer.",
    "answer": "<b><u>Harrenhal</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>The freefolk sometimes use this species to craft bows, spears, and arrows, and one door of the House of Black and White is made of the same material. While expensive, it serves as an excellent medium for building because its wood does not rot. This species is said to live forever if undisturbed, but the (*)</b> First Men feared it, and destroyed much of it in the south. The Knight of the Laughing Tree also carried an image of this tree on their shield. For 10 points, what is the name of the species of tree now primarily found in the north, the Isle of Faces, and godswoods?",
    "answer": "<b><u>weirwood</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>The dragons Balerion and Meraxes have names that originate from this language. Mongrel tongue, the language of some slavers, is a blend of this language and Old Ghiscari. Melisandre prays in this language, and in (*)</b> Astapor, Daenerys Targaryen pretends she doesn’t speak this language while conversing with the Good Masters. While obsidian is called \"dragonglass\" in the Common Tongue, it is translated to \"frozen fire\" in this language. Arya comments that Bravoosi shares some similarities with this language. For 10 points, name the language of the phrases <i>valar morghulis</i> and <i>dracarys</i>.",
    "answer": "<b>High <u>Valyrian</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>The daughter of a Whent, this individual has two older brothers who died in infancy. Her first pregnancy was aborted by her father, and she would come to suffer many more miscarriages and stillborn children. Her only son is named after a king, despite being (*)</b> fragile and unstable. Although she may not know it, this person was a primary instigator of the War of the Five Kings. She was murdered by her childhood love, and the crime was then blamed on the singer Marillion. For 10 points, name this known user of the Tears of Lys, and the late wife of Jon Arryn.",
    "answer": "<b><u>Lysa</u></b> Tully"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Loyalists to Rhaenyra Targaryen during the Dance of the Dragons adopted this color as their faction name, as opposed to the \"greens\" who stood for Aegon II. This color is not found in the sigils of House Arryn, Lannister, and Stark, but it does serve as the background sigil color for Houses Karstark and Greyjoy, as well as the color of House (*)</b> Baratheon’s stag. It’s not yellow, but this color helped Ned Stark deduce the true parentage of Cersei’s children, and a temple in Braavos contains this color in its name. For 10 points, what is this color also adopted by men of the Night’s Watch?",
    "answer": "<b><u>black</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Aegon the Fifth was against this practice and tried to put an end to it, but his children Jaeherys and Shaera did not share his views. The Valyrian Freehold nobles would have agreed with them. Stannis Baratheon used this act to support his claim to the throne, and (*)</b> Jon Arryn lost his life for discovering an instance of this practice. Daenerys had always assumed she would do it before meeting a certain horselord. For 10 points, name this act also practiced by the wildling Craster, as well as Cersei and Jaime Lannister.",
    "answer": "<b><u>incest</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>A knight of the Kingsguard is usually posted in this building, which is also where Queen Helaena Targaryen committed suicide. This fortress is where Elia Martell hid with her children during the Sack of King’s Landing, and highborn women and children also hid here during the (*)</b> Battle of the Blackwater. However, this makes escape difficult, as Varys claims there are virtually no secret passages in and out of this castle-within-a-castle. Sansa Stark is confined to its grounds in the days following her father’s execution. For 10 points, what is the name of the structure inside the Red Keep, named after King Maegor the Cruel?",
    "answer": "<b><u>Maegor's Holdfast</u></b> (prompt on <u>holdfast</u>)"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Also known as the Haunted Lands, this region allegedly was once the birthplace of civilization, but that predated the invention of writing. The Forest of Qohor borders it to the west and Slaver’s Bay to the south. Daenerys discovers she is pregnant while travelling through this inland area, and Drogon flies here following conflicts in (*)</b> Meereen. The name of this wasteland is a misnomer, which Victarion Greyjoy falls for upon initially hearing it. For 10 points, which region holds the Mother of Mountains, the Womb of the World, and the settlement of Vaes Dothrak, where the widows of khals live and rule?",
    "answer": "<b><u>Dothraki sea</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>A line from this song says, \"in a coat of gold or a coat of red, a lion still has claws.\" This song depicts a rebellion against House Lannister by one of its vassal houses, whose sigil is also a lion. The entire rebel house was executed, but its name is immortalized in the song’s title through punnery. Jaime Lannister plays this song for (*)</b> Edmure Tully as a threat to surrender Riverrun, and many singers sang this to please Tywin Lannister during Joffrey's wedding. For 10 points, which song also played prominently another wedding hosted by Walder Frey in The Twins?",
    "answer": "<b><u>The Rains of Castamere</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Rodrik Greyjoy, Willas Tyrell, Cersei Lannister, and Robb Stark all have this trait in common, and Randyll Tarly wishes Sam did not have it. Despite not possessing this trait, Edmure Tully is still the heir to Riverrun, which Dornish law would have opposed. (*)</b> Princess Arianne uses this trait as justification for crowning Myrcella over Tommen. Stannis frequently cites this trait as the reason he fights for the Iron Throne, upon Robert's death. For 10 points, identify this trait of Stannis used to justify his claim over his younger brother Renly.",
    "answer": "<b>being the <u>oldest</u> living <u>child</u></b> (accept obvious equivalents)"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Melisandre claims that when this object is used, the long night will begin. Mance Rayder uses this object as leverage against the Night's Watch to gain passage through the Wall, though Tormund later confides that it was not the real object. A common theory hypothesizes that it was hidden near the (*)</b> Fist of the First Men. While maesters are doubtful of its existence, the free folk tell tales of it from thousands of years ago when it was used to awaken giants from the earth. For 10 points, name this object said to bring down the Wall if blown, and is named after a former wildling king.",
    "answer": "<b><u>Horn of Joramun</u></b> (also accept <b><u>Horn of Winter</b></u> and <b><u>Joramun's Horn</u></b>)"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Bael the Bard once led these people, and House Stark is said to carry their blood. Men from this society search for wives from afar, and towns in the Gift often suffer from their raids. These people sometimes trade with men from Eastwatch-by-the-Sea, and (*)</b> two horn blasts on the Wall signals their arrival. When Jeor Mormont led rangers through their villages, he found them utterly abandoned. This tribe adamantly refuses to kneel. For 10 points, name this group of people, members of which include Ygritte and Tormund.",
    "answer": "<b><u>freefolk</u></b> (also accept <b><u>wildlings</u></b>)"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Robert's Rebellion began in this part of the realm, and some notable houses from here include Egen, Hunter, and Corbray. Years later, Tyrion Lannister recruits hundreds of swordsmen here without contacting any of these noble houses. Littlefinger uses (*)</b> Harrenhal as a stepping stone to gain control of this region, whose strength is said to match that of the North and Dorne. However, during the War of the Five Kings, houses from this region stayed steadfastly neutral, despite multiple pleas from blood relatives. For 10 points, name the land that houses a castle said to be impregnable, the Eyrie.",
    "answer": "<b><u>The Vale</u> of Arryn</b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>This city, which was built before the Andal invasion, is where the roseroad ends. This city is located in the Reach and has yielded to each new invader to Westeros. Jorah Mormont's disgruntled second wife came from this city's feudal house, which built a tremendously tall (*)</b> tower in the center of this city, even taller than the Wall's seven hundred feet. After Aegon's Conquest, King's Landing outgrew this place as the most populous city in the realm, though traders and students still flock to this place in great numbers. For 10 points, which city does Sam travel to from the Wall in order to become a maester at the Citadel?",
    "answer": "<b><u>Oldtown</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>The daughter of the <i>Myraham</i>'s captain wants to become this, and examples of houses that descend from these people are Codd and Humble. There exists a religious ceremony to officially bestow this label upon someone, but it is arguably more of an afterthought after the deed is done. Compared to their counterparts in Dorne, the (*)</b> paramours, these people are considered to have much lower societal status, and a man can have multiple of these women, who mainly come from raids. For 10 points, what name to The Ironborn give to their concubines?",
    "answer": "<b><u>salt wife</u></b> (prompt on <u>wife</u>)"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>This person won the tournament in honor of Viserys Targaryen's birth, and Rhaegar called him his oldest friend. He defeated the Kingswood Brotherhood, killed the Smiling Knight, and gained the trust of smallfolk by paying for everything he took. For this he is remembered as nothing but (*)</b> chivalrous, and even Jaime Lannister idolizes him. In fact, this person also happens to be the one who knighted young Jaime. This brave soldier served on Aerys's Kingsguard, and ultimately met his end at the Tower of Joy. For 10 points, which famed knight wielded the greatsword Dawn and is popularly known as the Sword of the Morning?",
    "answer": "<b>Ser <u>Arthur Dayne</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>This war occurred during the reign of King Jaehaerys II, when the crown fought against the Band of Nine. One of the commanders of this band was actually Jaeherys’s relative, Maelys the Monstrous. Lord Hoster Tully became close with House Baelish during this war, and subsequently took their son, Petyr, as his ward. Also known as the (*)</b> Fifth Blackfyre Rebellion, this war raised Ser Barristan Selmy to the limelight, who became the next knight named to the Kingsguard. For 10 points, name the war that Meribald thought was strangely named, having fought in it as a boy without seeing kings nor earning any pennies.",
    "answer": "<b>War of the <u>Ninepenny Kings</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>House Morrigen includes this animal in their sigil, and several mountain clans in the Vale are also named after this animal. Patchface claims these animals exist under the sea, and Maester Aemon claims them to be a poor cousin to another species. Euron Greyjoy’s personal coat-of-arms includes (*)</b> two of these animals supporting a black iron crown and a red eye. Bran often has dreams involving this animal, and Old Nan insists they are all liars. Brynden Rivers earns a title with this animal in its name. For 10 points, name the animal that the freefolk use to refer to men of the Night’s Watch.",
    "answer": "<b><u>crow</u>s</b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>The first knight of this house saved Lord Tytos Lannister from a lioness, but lost a leg in the process. A daughter from this house died under mysterious circumstances, but the other children go on to serve their liege lord. One son was knighted by Rhaegar Targaryen, but the other refused to be knighted at all. Both independently become involved in (*)</b> trials by combat, and both triumph as champions. Men in service of this house include Rafford, Polliver, and Chiswyck, but their leader was killed by Oberyn Martell. For 10 points, name this westerlands house of the Mountain and the Hound.",
    "answer": "<b>House <u>Clegane</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>This event started when Lord Denys Darklyn refused to pay taxes, after seeing his port city dwindle in trade due to the growth of another city nearby. He invites King Aerys II to hear his petition, but kidnaps him instead. Although Ser Barristan Selmy eventually rescues the king, this event is said to have caused Aerys’s (*)</b> madness and paranoia, who refused to leave the Red Keep for four years afterwards. As for Lord Denys’s punishment, House Darklyn was annihilated entirely, and their lands burned and redistributed. For 10 points, name the rebellious act that left Dontos Hollard as the sole surviving member of his house.",
    "answer": "<b><u>Defiance of Duskendale</u></b> (prompt on <u>Defiance</u> or <u>Duskendale</u>)"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>This ship is said to be famous from Ibben to Asshai, and is crewed by a staff of mutes and mongrels. On the ship's prow is a mouthless maiden of black iron. She only has a single mast with black sails, and her hull is dark red. The decks are also painted red to (*)</b> better hide the blood that soak them. Her captain was exiled from the Iron Islands for impregnating Victarion Greyjoy's wife, but he sails this ship back the day after Balon's death, with her cargo bay full of treasure to win ironborn support for the kingsmoot. For 10 points, name this fearsome galley commanded by Euron Greyjoy.",
    "answer": "<b><u>Silence</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>After Valyria conquered Rhoyne, this individual led the surviving Rhoynar to Dorne. Upon arrival, she wedded Lord Mors Martell, and together they ousted six other Dornish kings to establish control over the region. Her life inspired the book <i>Ten Thousand Ships</i>, and she is remembered as a \"warrior queen\". She is a hero in the eyes of Arianne Martell and (*)</b> Arya Stark, who names a fictional ship after her when inventing a backstory in Braavos. Back in Westeros, she also once used this person’s name as an alias, but shortened it to Nan. For 10 points, name the princess whose name is shared by Arya’s direwolf.",
    "answer": "<b><u>Nymeria</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Those who live in cold, damp climates are prone to this disease. Maesters aid victims with limes and scalding-hot baths, whereas septons insist on prayer, fasting, and sacrifice. This disease generally affects children, and begins with blackened fingertips and loss of sensation. The (*)</b> Bridge of Dream is often inhabited by victims of this disease, which is also where Jon Connington contracts it. The freefolk believe in giving its victims the gift of mercy, considering them unclean and a danger to others. For 10 points, name the disease of the stone men that Shireen Baratheon survived as an infant, which turns flesh stiff and grey.",
    "answer": "<b><u>greyscale</u></b> (also accept <b><u>grey plague</u></b>)"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>The majority of men fall under this classification in the Patrimony of Hyrkoon, and they serve their cities as scribes, priests, scholars, cooks, and farmers. Priests of the Blind God also fall under this category. Many other people with this label come from Yunkai, Astapor, and (*)</b> Meereen, and the <i>dosh khaleen</i> are also served by these people. Examples of other men like this include Strong Belwas and Ser Lucamore Strong. In Essos, most people with this label are slaves; in Westeros, they are more likely to be criminals. For 10 points, name the label that Varys and the Unsullied share.",
    "answer": "<b><u>eunuch</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>This individual is described as skinny, with straight hair, and his grandmother was a chandler. He grew up with his uncle Cedric and later served for a hedge knight, Ser Lorimer. Later, he is trained briefly by Ser Aron Santagar, master-at-arms of the (*)</b> Red Keep. He is so quiet that he is occasionally requested to stick out his tongue to confirm it is not lost, but proves his worth when he saves Tyrion Lannister from Ser Mandon Moore. Later, he follows Brienne of Tarth around on an old piebald rounsey horse. For 10 points, name this distant cousin of Ser Ilyn Payne, and Tyrion’s former squire.",
    "answer": "<b><u>Podrick</u> Payne</b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>A woman becomes this when presented with a wreath of flowers, and on one occasion, Eddard Stark remembers the laurel to be made of blue winter roses. Ser Criston Cole bestowed this upon Princess Rhaenyra Targaryen, and the Knight of Tears did the same to Queen Naerys. This process is part of how Lynesse Hightower became involved with (*)</b> Ser Jorah Mormont. This title is granted by the victor of a tourney, and can be a source of scandal if he chooses someone already bound to another man, or not his own wife. For 10 points, what did Rhaegar Targaryen name Lyanna Stark following his victory at the great tourney of Harrenhal?",
    "answer": "<b><u>queen of love and beauty</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Coldness will thicken this substance, but heating it will make it flow. It can seep into most other materials, like cloth, wood, leather, and steel, and the extinction of the dragons is said to have an effect on its creation. Caches of this substance are still found occasionally beneath the grounds of (*)</b> King’s Landing. A massive quantity of this was ordered in preparation for the Battle of the Blackwater, which was made carefully in bare stone cells by the Alchemists’ Guild. For 10 points, name the green substance that Aerys II planned on using to burn all of King’s Landing.",
    "answer": "<b><u>wildfire</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>Doran Martell feared this group of people, for they were stirring unrest in the streets of Sunspear. Its members come from places like Oldtown, Volantis, and the Summer Isles, with the youngest, Loreza, being barely seven years old. This band is later split and confined in the Spear Tower and the (*)</b> Water Gardens. This group’s name references a Dornish surname, and its members are said to share similar eye shapes, if not color. Princess Arianne Martell is fond of them, and laments one as the \"sweet sister that she never had\". For 10 points, what is the collective name for Oberyn Martell’s bastard daughters?",
    "answer": "<b><u>Sand Snakes</u></b>"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>This individual was once betrothed to Daeron Targaryen, but ended up with a husband from the Reach, who rode off a cliff to his death while hawking. She has a distaste for Targaryens and Martells, and has a jester named Butterbumps. Born originally into House Redwyne, this individual has two guardsmen she nicknames (*)</b> \"Left\" and \"Right\". She is a staunch supporter of her family and was highly skeptical of Joffrey Baratheon. Although she walks with a cane and claims to be near deaf, this person makes good use of her sharp tongue. For 10 points, name the Dowager Lady of Highgarden, the grandmother of Margaery Tyrell.",
    "answer": "<b><u>Olenna</u> Tyrell</b> (also accept <b><u>Olenna</u> Redwyne</b>; prompt on <u>Queen of Thorns</u>)"
  },
  {
    "question": "<b>During times of peace, this title is purely honorary. Those holding this title are responsible for their region’s defense, and have power as supreme military leaders. This title is usually hereditary, but the king can award it to another person; one example is upon Jon Arryn’s death, when King Robert bestows it to (*)</b> Jaime Lannister. During the Greyjoy Rebellion, two men holding this title were called upon to keep the king’s peace; these men were Eddard Stark and Tywin Lannister. Smaller regions with men like this include the Prince’s Pass, the Stone Way, and the White Knife. For 10 points, name the title that also exists for each of the four cardinal directions.",
    "answer": "<b><u>warden</u></b>"
  }
]